<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2022-12-11T22:09:54+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>A simple, whitespace theme for academics. Based on [*folio](https://github.com/bogoli/-folio) design.
</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Stable Diffusion</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2022/stable-diffusion/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Stable Diffusion" /><published>2022-12-10T16:12:00+01:00</published><updated>2022-12-10T16:12:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/2022/stable-diffusion</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/2022/stable-diffusion/">&lt;p&gt;So in April of this year (2022), OpenAI announced the release of the much-anticipated &lt;a href=&quot;https://openai.com/dall-e-2/&quot;&gt;DALL-E 2&lt;/a&gt;, an AI capable of generating digital images from natural language descriptions. The results were mindblowing as the level of details achieved, especially for faces, was on par with what humans could produce. One of the most famous pictures from DALL-E 2 is the star-gazing raccoon astronaut:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot; style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;col-sm-2&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;col-sm-8 mt-3 mt-md-0&quot;&gt;
        &lt;img class=&quot;img-fluid rounded z-depth-1&quot; src=&quot;/assets/img/stablediffusion/racoon_dalle2.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; title=&quot;example image&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;
    Image generated by DALL-E 2 using the following prompt: &quot;a raccoon astronaut with the cosmos reflecting on the glass of his helmet dreaming of the stars&quot;.
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few weeks later, Google announced &lt;a href=&quot;https://imagen.research.google/&quot;&gt;Imagen&lt;/a&gt;, a similar text-to-image model which was claimed at the time to be slightly better than DALL-E 2. APIs to generate images from prompts were soon released to the public for OpenAI and if you were among the first beta-testers you could generate images on-the-fly. However those models were really heavy and computationally expensive to run, even for inference so that generating those images locally on your laptop was out of reach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This all changed in August 2022 with the release of &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/CompVis/stable-diffusion&quot;&gt;Stable Diffusion&lt;/a&gt;, an open-source, optimized text-to-image model that could be run on a sufficiently powerful laptop with a GPU (such as Macs M1/M2). The idea of this new model is to train and generate images on a latent-space, much smaller than the high-resolution space of the actual images (a link to the paper &lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2112.10752&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have been very enthusiastic at the release of Stable Diffusion and wanted to try things out by myself so here is the beginning of my journey to become a prompt master! All the images created here have been done so with weights of Stable Diffusion v1.5 with the &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/invoke-ai/InvokeAI&quot;&gt;InvokeAI&lt;/a&gt; fork of the original repository on GitHub.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think the most amazing thing about Stable Diffusion is that it allows a lot of people without any drawing/painting talent 🧑‍🎨 (that includes me) to create complex and beautiful images. It still takes time to become a prompt master as there are a lot of additional keywords necessary to create something close to what you have in mind. Several pages have helped me refine my skills in that regard: &lt;a href=&quot;https://mpost.io/best-100-stable-diffusion-prompts-the-most-beautiful-ai-text-to-image-prompts/&quot;&gt;Best 100+ Stable Diffusion Prompts&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://strikingloo.github.io/stable-diffusion-vs-dalle-2&quot;&gt;Stable Diffusion: Prompt Guide and Examples&lt;/a&gt; among others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are only prompting from text to image you are likely to produce astonishing images but you lose some kind of control about the exact shape and positioning of things in your image. This is fun at the beginning but my intent with Stable Diffusion was to reproduce images that I had in my head. A very exciting feature in Stable Diffusion is that you can give it a sketch of yours as a first guess and it will “enhance” your image depending on your prompt. The first example can be found below where I used &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Seashore&lt;/code&gt; (an equivalent of Paint on Mac) to draw a rather childish sketch of a mountain with a river that I turned into an oil painting thanks to Stable Diffusion:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row justify-content-sm-center&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;col-sm-6 mt-3 mt-md-0&quot;&gt;
        &lt;img class=&quot;img-fluid rounded z-depth-1&quot; src=&quot;/assets/img/stablediffusion/mountains_clouds.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; title=&quot;example image&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;col-sm-6 mt-3 mt-md-0&quot;&gt;
        &lt;img class=&quot;img-fluid rounded z-depth-1&quot; src=&quot;/assets/img/stablediffusion/mountains_clouds_painting.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; title=&quot;example image&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;
    Original image created using Seashore (left). Image generated using Stable Diffusion v1.5 and the following prompt: &quot;oil painting of flowing river, mountains with cloud, hyper realistic grass, sunset, turner, 4k, detailed, nature photograph, national geographic&quot; -f 0.85 (right)
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The result is quite impressive as the childish sketch has been tranformed to something much prettier (to me at least). I had quite some trouble turning directly the original sketch into a realistic picture, I found that it is easier for the model to transform any sketch to a painting as it blurs things out. So in a second step I started from this oil painting to generate a photorealistic view of my initial sketch (left image of the figure below). I was not quite happy with the mountain itself so I used a feature of the model to replace the mountain by another one in the image so that last one was closer to what I had in mind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row justify-content-sm-center&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;col-sm-6 mt-3 mt-md-0&quot;&gt;
        &lt;img class=&quot;img-fluid rounded z-depth-1&quot; src=&quot;/assets/img/stablediffusion/mountains_clouds_image.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; title=&quot;example image&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;col-sm-6 mt-3 mt-md-0&quot;&gt;
        &lt;img class=&quot;img-fluid rounded z-depth-1&quot; src=&quot;/assets/img/stablediffusion/mountains_clouds_inpainting.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; title=&quot;example image&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;
    &quot;oil painting of flowing river, mountains with cloud, hyper realistic grass, sunset, turner, 4k, detailed, nature photograph, national geographic &quot; -f 0.9 (left). &quot;snowy mountain, hyper realistic, national geographic&quot; (right)
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;gallery&quot;&gt;Gallery&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are some other snapshots of images that I have created using the same mechanism: sketch on Seashore, painting and then image (if applicable). The prompts can be found in the captions 😊.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row justify-content-sm-center&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;col-sm-4 mt-3 mt-md-0&quot;&gt;
        &lt;img class=&quot;img-fluid rounded z-depth-1&quot; src=&quot;/assets/img/stablediffusion/city_night.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; title=&quot;example image&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;col-sm-4 mt-3 mt-md-0&quot;&gt;
        &lt;img class=&quot;img-fluid rounded z-depth-1&quot; src=&quot;/assets/img/stablediffusion/city_night_painting.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; title=&quot;example image&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;col-sm-4 mt-3 mt-md-0&quot;&gt;
        &lt;img class=&quot;img-fluid rounded z-depth-1&quot; src=&quot;/assets/img/stablediffusion/city_night_photo.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; title=&quot;example image&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;
    Sketch of a city at night (left). &quot;oil painting of a city at night, josef thomas, dim light&quot; (middle). &quot;city at night, winter, dim light, photograph, highly detailed, ultra realistic, 4k&quot; (right)
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row justify-content-sm-center&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;col-sm-6 mt-3 mt-md-0&quot;&gt;
        &lt;img class=&quot;img-fluid rounded z-depth-1&quot; src=&quot;/assets/img/stablediffusion/boats_sunset.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; title=&quot;example image&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;col-sm-6 mt-3 mt-md-0&quot;&gt;
        &lt;img class=&quot;img-fluid rounded z-depth-1&quot; src=&quot;/assets/img/stablediffusion/two_boats_night.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; title=&quot;example image&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;
    Sketch of two boats at sunset (left). Sketch of two boats under a full moon (right)
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row justify-content-sm-center&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;col-sm-6 mt-3 mt-md-0&quot;&gt;
        &lt;img class=&quot;img-fluid rounded z-depth-1&quot; src=&quot;/assets/img/stablediffusion/boats_sunset_painting.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; title=&quot;example image&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;col-sm-6 mt-3 mt-md-0&quot;&gt;
        &lt;img class=&quot;img-fluid rounded z-depth-1&quot; src=&quot;/assets/img/stablediffusion/two_boats_night_painting.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; title=&quot;example image&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;
    &quot;two boats sailing in the open ocean at sunset, some clouds, caspar david friedrich, detailed, 4k&quot; -f 0.9 (left). &quot;two boats sailing under a full moon at night, sky full of stars, white sailes, oil painting, turner, 4k, detailed&quot; -f 0.8 (right)
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">So in April of this year (2022), OpenAI announced the release of the much-anticipated DALL-E 2, an AI capable of generating digital images from natural language descriptions. The results were mindblowing as the level of details achieved, especially for faces, was on par with what humans could produce. One of the most famous pictures from DALL-E 2 is the star-gazing raccoon astronaut:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">BIG Quantum Hackaton</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2021/quantum/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="BIG Quantum Hackaton" /><published>2021-10-05T17:12:00+02:00</published><updated>2021-10-05T17:12:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/2021/quantum</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/2021/quantum/">&lt;p&gt;I had the chance to spend 4 days at the BIG Quantum Hackaton organized in Paris from October 2nd to October 5th 2021 by &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.quantx.fr&quot;&gt;QuantX&lt;/a&gt;, the alumni association from Ecole Polytechnique on quantum physics. Two days were dedicated to a technical phase, from which 5 projects out of 10 were selected to continue in a business phase.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Les Atomes de Savoie team which I was a part of had to work on waveform optimization using quantum circuit, a problem proposed by Thales to enhance the resolution of their radars. Phase modulation is used on an electromagnetic wave by dividing it in \(N\) chunks in order to precisely measure the time of the reflection. Having a larger number of chunks increases the accuracy of the radar so the higher the \(N\), the better. Finding the waveform for a given \(N\) is a complex combinatorial problem where for large \(N\) the space of configurations can be huge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot; style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0&quot;&gt;
        &lt;img class=&quot;img-fluid rounded z-depth-1&quot; src=&quot;/assets/img/quantum/waveform.gif&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; title=&quot;example image&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;
    Phase reconstruction of a signal.
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Quantum reformulation of the problem allowed us to use Quantum Approximate Optimization Algorithm (QAOA) to tackle this problem and find optimal configurations. The algorithm was not nearly as robust and fast as classical algorithms but the task of reformulating the problem in a quantum framework alone is an interesting exercice. The power coming from the \(2^n\) vector space spanned by \(n\) qubits is always promising for such a large space of possible configurations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The benefits of quantum computing are not yet understood in every field and this is why so many companies like BMW or Thales invest it although the return on investment is far from being immediate. Lots of things are not settled in quantum computing but the most pressing issue seems to be qubit reliability. Many algorithms are ready for deployment but the hardware is not here yet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row justify-content-sm-center&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;col-sm-7 mt-3 mt-md-0&quot;&gt;
        &lt;img class=&quot;img-fluid rounded z-depth-1&quot; src=&quot;/assets/img/quantum/technical.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; title=&quot;example image&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;col-sm-5 mt-3 mt-md-0&quot;&gt;
        &lt;img class=&quot;img-fluid rounded z-depth-1&quot; src=&quot;/assets/img/quantum/business.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; title=&quot;example image&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;
    Les Atomes de Savoie with Luca Mondada from Pytket and Alexandre Krajenbrink, organizer of the Hackaton (left). Les Fonds du Savoyard (right)
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finishing second at the end of the technical phase, Tristan and I went on to help the business team (Les Fonds du Savoyard) assigned to our case understand the new technical possibilities that could be achieved by solving our initial problem. Seeing how technical improvement can be monetized and pitched was a great experience from a PhD student point of view, opening my eyes on the business side of things. Pitching a satellite company project called &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;QubitSat&lt;/code&gt; to leverage the increased accuracy that quantum computing could achieve, the business team also finished second!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Quantum computing is only at an early stage but the energy and excitement are there! The scope of things to do is limitless and I am rather confident in the fact that quantum computing will change our lives in the coming decades.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">I had the chance to spend 4 days at the BIG Quantum Hackaton organized in Paris from October 2nd to October 5th 2021 by QuantX, the alumni association from Ecole Polytechnique on quantum physics. Two days were dedicated to a technical phase, from which 5 projects out of 10 were selected to continue in a business phase.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Taking scientific notes efficiently using Markdown + KaTeX</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2021/notes/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Taking scientific notes efficiently using Markdown + KaTeX" /><published>2021-10-03T17:12:00+02:00</published><updated>2021-10-03T17:12:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/2021/notes</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/2021/notes/">&lt;p&gt;As a PhD student, reading scientific articles and textbooks has occupied a significant amount of my time. I have been at some point overwhelmed by the quantity of knowledge to process and synthesize at the same time. Here is the workflow that I have found to try to keep up to date with all the research projects that I have going on. It involves &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;VSCode&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Markdown&lt;/code&gt; and a little library that I have written &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/lionelchg/Markdown2LaTeX&quot;&gt;Markdown2LaTeX&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have been taking notes on paper notebooks for quite a long time at the beginning of my PhD, stacking them one on top of the other over time. When I wanted to go back to some thoughts that I had it was always a tedious process to find them back in my pile of notebooks. After that I would usually start writing a TeX about it, translating whatever I had written a while ago. This workflow had several drawbacks: it was not easy to back go over ideas that I had at some point and remembering exactly what I was thinking at that time. Since ideas at the beginning are not well formed and finished it does not really make sense to write it to TeX at that moment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then I discovered &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Markdown&lt;/code&gt; in &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;VSCode&lt;/code&gt; using Markdown Preview. This tool allows to write down &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Markdown&lt;/code&gt; and instantly see your writings on a side tab (see screenshot below). Using KaTeX, it is possible to write math as TeX quickly and efficiently with a real time synchronization on the preview tab (definitions of KaTeX macros is also possible). I have since created a single workspace to hold all my Markdown notes files (creating symbolic links whenever necessary). It has allowed me to take and store notes at the same place and is also a great tool to interact with others during visioconferences without needing to scribble some complicated math formula on your notebook and then showing it on the webcam.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0&quot;&gt;
        &lt;img class=&quot;img-fluid rounded z-depth-1&quot; src=&quot;/assets/img/notes/katex_demo.gif&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; title=&quot;example image&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;
    Markdown Preview in VSCode.
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Markdown+Math&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Markdown Preview Enhanced&lt;/code&gt; extensions from &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;VSCode&lt;/code&gt; need to be downloaded and then you can start writing math using &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;$$...$$&lt;/code&gt; delimiters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Taking this logic a step further, after a Markdown file is written and cleaned, it can be converted directly into a LaTeX file using &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/lionelchg/Markdown2LaTeX&quot;&gt;Markdown2LaTeX&lt;/a&gt;. Running the following command&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-shell highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;md2latex &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;-f&lt;/span&gt; demo.md &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;-m&lt;/span&gt; macros.md
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;allows to retrieve the LaTeX file. A file where KaTeX macros are defined can be supplemented and macros can be converted to TeX format.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0&quot;&gt;
        &lt;img class=&quot;img-fluid rounded z-depth-1&quot; src=&quot;/assets/img/notes/markdown2latex.gif&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; title=&quot;example image&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;
    Markdown file converted to LaTeX file and resulting pdf.
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">As a PhD student, reading scientific articles and textbooks has occupied a significant amount of my time. I have been at some point overwhelmed by the quantity of knowledge to process and synthesize at the same time. Here is the workflow that I have found to try to keep up to date with all the research projects that I have going on. It involves VSCode, Markdown and a little library that I have written Markdown2LaTeX.</summary></entry></feed>